Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 3: Winter Quarters of the French Army in Virginia, 1781-1782, 1781 October-1782 April 5; portions of 2 portfolios
  - 106. Plan d'Hampton pour servir a l'Etablissement du Quartier d'hiver de la Legion de L'auzun, le 1 9bre, 1781, undated; 1 item 39 x 31.5 cm (on 42.5 x 36 cm sheet) (Portfolio X, Packet 28)
    During the French "occupation" of Hampton the courthouse (serving Elizabeth City County) was used as a hospital. This is the unnumbered building shown on the map a bit to the left of King Street directly below the second "u" of "Lauzun" in the title. An Act of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Virginia (5 January 1782) empowered the lustices of the peace in the said county as they may think proper, so long as the court-house in the town of Hampton shall be occupied by the troops of our allies, as a hospital." The names of several French soldiers who died in Hampton (including Carette, Thouvenot, and Bourdet of the Saintonge Regiment) are mentioned in Bouvet, Service de santé, p. 94, and in Dawson, Français Morts aux Etats-Unis, pp. 60, 64, 65, 92.
    MS, Princeton University Library, Berthier Collection, No. 28. [Rice/Brown, pp. 170-171]
    Regarding movement of Saintonge Regiment cf. Beville's "Ordre de marche" of 28 June 1782 (Library of Congress, Rochambeau Papers, Vol. 4, 469
  - 99. Plan d'York-Town pour servir a l'Etablissement du Quartier d'hyver du Regiment de Soissonnois; et des Grenadiers et Chasseurs de St. Onge, le 12 novembre, 1781, undated; 1 item 28 x 46.5 cm (Portfolio X, Packet 29)
    Plan of Yorktown to be Used for Establishing the Winter Quarters of the Soissonnais Regiment, and of the Grenadiers and Chasseurs of the Saintonge Regimen. 12 November 1781. This map provides a record of Yorktown buildings as they existed immediately after the siege. At the upper left (colored darker than the others) is "Secretary Nelson's" house, where Cornwallis has his headquarters at the opening of the siege and which later suffered heavily from allied artillery bombardment. The building set back slightly from the south side of the main street (below the word "hyver" in the heading) was another Nelson house belonging to Secretary Nelson's nephew, Thomas Nelson, Jr., governor of Virginia and commander of the merican militia during the siege. Both Nelson houses figure in the annals of the siege; see, e.g., Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal, n. 137.
    MS, No. 29. [Rice/Brown, p. 165]
    The Thomas Nelson, Jr., house ("York Hall"), still standing, can be distinguished in the distant view of Yorktown included in Van Blarenberghe's paintings (Nos. 92 and 95). See also the "View of York," which was drawn at about the same time as this ground plan and which is similarly oriented, with the York River in the foreground. Other buildings surviving today (the Customs House, Grace Church, etc.) may be identified by reference to the map of "Old Houses and Other Places of Interest in the 'Town of York,'" in Charles E. Hatch, Jr., Yorktown and the Siege of 1781, National Park Service, Historical Handbook No. 14 (Washington, 1954, and subsequent editions).
  - 107. Établissement des hussards en Correspondance a New-Kent Courte House, New-Castle, et Linch Taverne, 1781, undated; 1 item 31 x 19.5 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 30)
    Chain of Expresses between New Kent Courthouse, New Castle, and Lynch's Tavern, 1781. Early in November, a few weeks after the capitulation of Yorktown, Washington's Continentals left Virginia and returned northward to winter quarters on the Hudson. The French army thus remained in an "intermediary position," as Rochambeau described it, between the Northern army and the Southern army in the Carolinas under the command of General Greene. In instructions to Colonel Timothy Pickering, dated Williamsburg, 4 November 1781, Washington had noted: "For the purpose of Communicating Intelligence, I have agreed with Count Rochambeau who remains here to establish a Chain of Expresses from hence to Philadelphia. You will take Measures to furnish your part of the Chain, which is to extend from the Bowling Green to Philadelphia; from the Bowling Green to this place [Williamsburg], extending towards Genl Greene, will be continued by Count Rochambeau." Writings of GW, XXIII, 331.
    The diagram and related memoranda prepared by L.-A. Berthier (a good example of the kind of assignments he received as an assistant quarter-master-general) show the "part of the chain" maintained by the French. Instructions for the two hussars stationed at New Kent Courthouse, dated 9 November, specify that they will remain there night and day ready to relay dispatches between Williamsburg and Richmond or to the next post as New Castle; the tavernkeeper at New Kent [James Warren] will feed the men and supply forage for their horses ("2 gallons of oats and 17 bunches of cornstalks per day"). Agreements also recorded here by Berthier mention that the tavernkeeper at New Kent is to be paid 50 dollars a month, those at New Castle and at Lynch's Tavern 40 dollars.
    Berthier was already familiar with this country, having traversed it when marching southward with the wagon train only a few weeks earlier; see Itinerary 6. New Castle, on the Pamunkey River, once a flourishing town, is now extinct. Lynch's Tavern (also known as "Head Lynch's Ordinary," from the name of the tavernkeeper, James Head Lynch) was near Reedy Creek about halfway between the Pamunkey and Mattaponi rivers along the road corresponding to present U.S. Route 301.
    It evidently took the Americans some time to establish satisfactory service beyond Bowling Green to Philadelphia. Rochambeau, for example, complained to Governor Benjamin Harrison of Virginia that a month after Washington's departure from Virginia he had not received a single letter from him. In a letter addressed to Beville, French quartermast-general, 5 December 1781, Richard Young reported from Fredericksburg: "If money cannot be obtain'd for the purpose of paying the Express Riders at the different posts [between Lynch's Tavern and Fredericksburg] it will be impossible to keep up a line of Communication.. .." Manuscript Collections of Colonial Williamsburg, Miscellaneous Manuscripts. Writing from Philadelphia, 8 January 1782, Washington avowed to Rochambeau: "I am fearful that the Expresses between this place and Williamsburg are badly regulated, and I shall upon the reutrn of the Quarter Master General from the North River endeavour to have things put in better train." Writings of GW, XXIII, 435.
    MS, 3 pages (4th blank), No. 30. Several other memoranda relating to the expresses are in Berthier papers, Nos. 32-37. [Rice/Brown, pp. 171-172]
    Cf. letters from Harrison to Rochambeau, 17 December, 21 December, and Harrison to Governor Thomas Sim Lee of Maryland, 21 December 1781, in H. R. McIlvaine, ed., Official Letters of the Governors of the State of Virginia, III (Richmond, 1929), 113, 116-117, regarding Rochambeau's complaints.
  - Note on a Trip from Fredericksburg to Col. D'[?]'s House, 1781 October; 1 item small slip of paper, with writing on both sides (Portfolio XII, Packet 31)
    Date uncertain, perhaps Oct. 2, 1781.
  - Billeting Order, 1781 November; 1 item 2 autograph documents on same page. 1 sheet. (Portfolio XII, Packet 32)
    Agreement (in English) signed by Philip Pendleton (at top) and agreement (in French) signed by Dumas (at bottom), Todsbridge, 13-14 Nov. 1781, for lodging of two hussards at Philip Pendleton's tavern in Todsbridge.
  - Pendleton's Agreement to Lodge the Two Hussards, dates not examined; 1 item Autograph document. 1 sheet. (Portfolio XII, Packet 33)
    Signed by Pendleton, together with another copy of Dumas' order, Nov. 14, 1781, signed by him on verso
  - Statement Signed by Dumas (aide Maréchal des logis de l'Armée), 1781 November 12; 1 item 1 p autograph document (Portfolio XII, Packet 34)
    Addressed Ruffin's Ferry, Nov. 12, 1781, for two hussards posted at Ruffin's Ferry.
  - Receipt for Two Dollars from Berthier, 1781 November 21; 1 item 1 p autograph document (Portfolio XII, Packet 35)
    For conducting him from Tod's Bridge to Head Lynch's Tavern, signed by Weste Hewitt, Nov. 21, 1781.
  - Letter from James Warren to Monsieur Berthier, 1782 March 30; 1 item 1 p autograph signed letter (Portfolio XII, Packet 36)
    Addressed from New Kent Court House, March 30, 1782, protesting that he can no longer lodge two hussards without additional pay.
  - Copy of Berthier's Reply to James Warren, 1782 April 5; 1 item autograph letter (Portfolio XII, Packet 37)
    Addressed from Williamsburg, April 5, 1782, insisting that Warren keep their previous agreement.
- Series 4: Return of the French Army from Virgina to Boston, July - December, 1782, dates not examined; more than 48 packets
  Maps documenting the return of the French Army from Virginia to Boston, July-December, 1782.
  Maps are arranged chronologically by sequential packet number.
  - Amerique - Campagne 1782: Etat des différents camps occupés par l'armée française, undated; 1 item 3 pp (Portfolio XII, Packet 38)
    List of French Army's campsites, nos. 1-54, from Drinking Spring, Virginia (July 1, 1782) to Dedham, Massachusetts (December 1782).
  - 108. Plans des différents camps occupés par l'Armée aux ordres de M. Le comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 46 packets 46 pp 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39)
    Maps of French Army's Campsites 1-55, from Drinking Spring to Dedham, Massachusetts. The following series of maps depicts the army's camps on its march from Virginia to the Hudson and eventually to Boston. The cover sheet of the "cahier," reproduced here, is the same as the one for the 1781 south-bound camps (No. 26) except for the heading "Amérique/ Campagne/ 1782." As with the earlier series, the maps are so oriented that the direction of the march (generally northward in 1782) is at the top of the sheet; thus the two series appear reversed in relation to each other. In instances where the army camped in 1782 on a site previously occupied in 1781 the cartographer has not repeated the map; the camp is merely recorded in the heading, with a cross-reference to the 1781 map. There are no detailed road maps for the 1782 marches. The route from Williamsburg to Spurrier's Tavern (19th camp, preceding the 20th camp at Baltimore) is described mile by mile in Itinerary 6, which records the march of the wagon train when it took this route in the opposite direction in 1781.
    The army moved northward from Williamsburg in four divisions, marching a day apart. The First Division, including the Bourbonnais Regiment, commanded by Major General Chastellux and led by Collot, left on 1 July; the Second Division, including the Royal Deux-Ponts, commanded by Comte Christian de Deux-Ponts and led by Cromot Bubourg, on 2 July; the Third Division, including the Soissonnais, commanded by Comte de Viomenil and led by his nephew Comte d'Ollone, on 3 July; the Fourth Division, including the Saintonge, commanded by Comte de Custine and led by the younger Berthier (Charles-Louis), on 4 July. Meanwhile, the Lauzun Legion had left Petersburg (see note to No. 106) and proceeded via Kingsland Ferry, Richmond, North's Tavern on the Chickahominy, and Hanover Courthouse, to Littlepage's Bridge on the Pamunkey, at which point it became the vanguard of the army, preceding it by two days. The Legion was commanded by the Marquis de Choisy (Lauzun himself had not yet returned from France) and led by Dumas and the elder Berthier (Louis-Alexandre). Rochambeau, who went ahead to confer with Washington in Philadelphia, did not personally accompany the army on the first stages of the march.
    MS, No. 39. Rochambeau's set of these camp plans is recorded in Philip L. Philips, A List of Maps of America in the Library of Congress (Washington, 1901), pp. 861-862. A somewhat similar series of the 1782 camp, but smaller in size, is in the Huntington Library, MS 621, described above in the "Checklist of Journals," s.v. Soissonnais Regiment. [Rice/Brown, pp. 172-174]
    Portions of the route through Virginia and Maryland can be traced in Christopher Colles, A Survey of the Roads of the United States of America (1789; facsimile, ed. Walter W. Ristow, 1961), Plates 59-80.
    A second set of the 1782 camp maps, which once belonged to General Rochambeau, is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. There are a few minor variations, such as uncompleted place names, in the General's set.
    The plan for the march is outlined in a document dated Williamsburg, 28 June 1782, signed by Bélville, quartermaster-general: "Ordre de Marche pour porter l'armée Françoise aux ordres de M. le Cte. de Rochambeau de ses différens Quartiers en Virginie à George-town sur la Rive gauche du Potowmak où Elle doit rester jusqu'à nouvel ordre en 22 jours de marche y compris Quatre Séjours" (Library of Congress, Rochambeau Papers, Vol. 4, 469-478).
    The march is briefly described in the journal of Clermont-Crèvecœur, who was with a company of the Auxonne artillery included in the Third Division (pp. 72 ff.); and also, in more detail, in the journal of Verger, of the Deux-Ponts Regiment, Second Division (pp. 159ff.).
    - 109. Camp à Drinking Springs, Le ler Juillet, 8 miles de Williamsburg, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-1)
      First Camp at Drinking Spring [in Virginia]. 1-4 July 1782. The dates on this and the following maps are those of the arrival of the first of the four divisions. The camp was thus occupied on four successive days.
      Drinking Spring, 8 miles northwest of Williamsburg, was along the road now known as U.S. Route 60. The camp ground was situated at present Norge in the vicinity of Our Savior Lutheran Church, where the small creek shown on the map can still be discerned.
      MS, No. 39-1. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 174]
    - 110. Camp 2 Miles au de la de Byrd's Tavern, Le 2 Juillet, 8 miles de Drinking Spring, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-2)
      Second Camp Two Miles beyond Byrd's Tavern. 2-5 July 1782. Eight miles from the previous camp. Byrd's (frequently written "Bird's") Tavern was earlier known as Doncastle's Ordinary and was situated about 2 miles south of present Barhamsville. Since the French camped 2 miles beyond the tavern (which is not shown on the map), this would seem to place their camp at Barhamsville. The road branching off to the ight, not taken by the army, led to Ruffin's Ferry, which crossed the Pamunkey above West Point.
      MS, No. 39-2. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 174]
    - 111. Camp à Rattelasse House, Le 3 Juillet, 7 miles de Byrd's Tavern." 3-6 July 1782, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-3)
      Third Camp at Ratcliffe House. Seven miles from Byrd's Tavern (i.e., 5 miles from the previous camp, which was 2 miles beyond the tavern). The much corrected word "Rattelaffe" appears to be a copying error for "Ratcliffe." There was evidently some uncertainty about the correct form. Verger in his journal writes it as "Radelassen." It has been variously transcribed in printed versions of other French officers' journals: e.g., "Ratelof" (Blanchard) and "Ratilisse" (Vicomte de Rochambeau).
      Although the exact location of the Ratcliffe property shown here has not been determined, it was probably along the present secondary road that goes from Barhamsville, via Slatersville, to New Kent Courthouse. The stream shown on the map may perhaps be a portion of Beaverdam Creek. Cf. U.S. Geological Survey, Wlakers Quadrangle.
      MS, No. 39-3. A similar map is in Rochambeau's set, Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 174]
      The name "Ratcliff" appears several times in the New Kent County Land Tax List for 1782 (earliest extant tax records for this county, Virginia State Library). "Ratcliffe"s also appear in the Vestry Book of Blissland Parish, part of which coincided with the eastern part of New Kent County; C. G. Chamberlayne, ed., The Vestry Book of Blisland (Blissland) Parish (Richmond, 1935).
    - 112. Camp à Hartfield. Le 4 Juillet, 7 miles de Rattelasse House, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-4)
      Fourth Camp at Hartfield. 4-7 July 1782. Seven and one half miles from the previous camp. The name "Hartfield," which should presumably read "Harfield," has disappeared from modern maps. A Micheal Harfield appears in the New Kent County Tax List for 1782 (Virginia State Library), and Harfields are also mentions in the Vestry Book of St. Peter's Parish, part of which coincided with the western part of this county. Itinerary 6 describes the position near "Hartfield House" (the building shown here on a small round hillock) as a very poor campsite. It was located some 3 miles northwest of New Kent Courthouse (through which the army had marches on its way here), alond the old road to New Castle. The creek flowing into the Pamunkey, shown here on the map, is perhaps Big Creek or White House Creek. Cf. U.S. Geological Survey, Tunstall Qadrangle. The site of "The White House" home of Martha Dandridge Custis at the time of her marriage to George Washington, is in this general region, as is the Pamunkey Indian Reservation across the river.
      MS, No. 39-4. Another copy (formerly in the archives of General Rochamebau) is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, pp. 174-175]
    - 113. Camp à New Castle, 1 mile en deça de la Ville, Le 5 Juillet, 15 miles de Hartfield. Le 6, Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-5)
      Fifth Camp at New Castle. 5-9 July 1782. Fifteen miles from the precious camp. There was an extra day's here for each of the divisions, so that two divisions were encamped here together on 6, 7, and 8 July, the Fourth Division only of the 9th. Itinerary 6, describing the wagon train's 1781 march, speaks of New Castle as "a small town with very few houses, situarted on high ground. It is almost deserted. There are many plantations in the neighborhood." More than a half century later, when Benson J. Lossing visited it in December 1848, he described it as "once a flourishing village, but now a desolation, only one house remaining upon its site" ( Pictorial Field-Book of the Revolution [New York, 1851], II, 225). With the decline of river traffic and the changing pattern of agricultural economy in this section of Virginia, New Castle has now wholly disappeared. It was situated a mile of so east of the present bridge over the Pamunky on the Richmond-Tappahanock road (U.S. Route 360), where a state historical marker recals Patrick Henry's "call to arms" at New Castle.
      MS, No. 39-5. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 175]
    - 114. Camp à Hannover Town un mile au de là de la Ville, Le 7 Juillet, 7 miles de New Castle, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-6)
      Sixth Camp at Hanovertown. 7-10 July 1782. Seven miles from the previous camp. Hanovertown (not to be confused with Hanover Courthouse, which was some 10 miles beyond to the northwest) has, like New Castle, disappeared from modern maps. The French camp was a mile beyond the little town shown here, which had been laid out by vote of the Virginia Assembly in 1762 near Page's Warehouse. The small stream on the map is a tributary of the Pamunkey. The wagon train had camped here on 4 October 1781; see Itinerary 6, where it is recorded that Hanovertown and vicinity had suffered considerable damage from Cornwallis's raiders.
      MS, No. 39-6. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 175]
    - 115. Camp à Peage's Bridge ou Graham's. Le 8 Juillet, 10 miles de Hannover Town, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-7)
      Seventh Camp at [Little] Page's Bridge or Graham's House. 8-10 July 1782. Ten miles from the previous camp. Littlepage's Bridge crossed the Pamunkey in the vicinity of Hanover Courthouse (not shown on the map). Graham's House was a mile of so beyond the river on the road (roughly present U.S. Route 301) leading north to Bowling Green. Itinerary 6 notes that the crossing of the Pamunkey was by a "wooden bridge." It was here at Littlepage's Bridge that the route of march of Lauzun's Legion (which had come from Petersburg and Richmond) joined that of the rest of the army. From here on the Legion formed the vanguard.
      MS, No. 39-7. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 176]
    - 116. Camp à Burck bridge ou Kenner's Tavern, Le 9 Juillet, 12 miles de Peage's Bridge, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-8)
      Eighth camp ar Burk's Bridge or Kenner's Tavern. 9-12 July 1782. Twelve miles from the previous camp. Burk's Bridge, which crossed the Mattaponi some 9 mile south of Bowling Green, was in Caroline County along present U.S. Route 301. John Burk was licensed as a tavernkeeper there. Although the wagon train did not camp at Burk's Bridge in 1781, the Itinerary describing its route notes that "a camp could be located in front of Burk's Brudge." "Kenner's Tavern" (the building to the left of the letter "k") is called "Kenner's Red House" on Colles's 1789 road map (Plate 72); the Itinerary (1781) refers to it only as "the red house."
      MS, No. 39-8. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 176]
    - 117. Camp à Bowling-green, Le 10 Juillet, 9 miles de Burck bridge, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-9)
      Ninth Camp at Bowling Green. 10-13 July 1782. Nine miles from the precious camp. Rochambeau's aide-de-camp Von Closen, who joined his regiment (Royal Deux-Ponts) here on 11 July, describes Bowling Green as "a small place where there is only one tavern and the residence of Mr. John Hoomes, a very wealthy person, where we danced in the evening" (p. 210). The road branching off to the right, as indicated on the map, led to Caroline Courthouse, which was some distance from the settlement at Bowling Green proper. A few years later the county seat was moved to Bowling Green, where the present county courthouse was erected on land provided for public use by John Hoomes. The wagon train had made its 10th camp here on 2 October 1781. See Itinerary 6, where it is noted: "Neither camp nor headquarters would be very well situated here. It is nevertheless better than any other campsite in this neighborhood."
      MS, No. 39-9. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Congress, Map Division. [Rice/Brown, p. 176]
    - 118. Camp à Charles Thoon-Ton's house, Le 11 Juillet, 8 miles de Bowling-green, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio XII, Packet 39-10)
      Tenth Camp at Charles Thornton's House. 11-14 July 1782. Eight and one half miles from the previous camp. The camp was on high ground beyond Charles Thornton's house on the road leading north to Fredericksburg and Falmouth. Some 2 miles beyond the campsite, but not shown on the map, was Todd's Ordinary (present Villboro, Caroline Country) where, according to Von Closen (p. 210), the headquarters was located. "Charles" Thornton's house was evidently so designated in order to distinguish it from "Widow" Thornton's, another "Fine house," 2 miles or so to the south and past which the army had marched on its way to its camp. Both Thornton houses are mentioned in the Itinerary (6) of the wagon train and are shown in Colles's Survey, Plates 70-71. When proceeding southward the wagon train had stopped to the east of the present route, at Colonel Dangerfield's plantation on the banks of the Rappahannock, as described in a fragment of Berthier's journal, Itinerary 6, n. 33.